Hi everyone, and welcome to the first lesson of the Generative AI for Beginners course.
This course is based on an open source curriculum with the same name available on GitHub.
I'm Carlotta Castelluccio, AI Cloud Advocate at Microsoft, and in this video I'm going
to introduce you to Generative AI and large language models.
Large language models represent the pinnacle of AI technology, pushing the boundaries of
what was once thought impossible.
They've conquered numerous challenges that older language models struggled with, achieving
human level performance in various tasks.
They have several capabilities and applications, but for this course we'll explore how large
language models are revolutionizing education through a fictional startup that we'll be
referring to as our startup.
Our startup works in the education domain with the ambitious mission of improving accessibility
in learning on a global scale, ensuring equitable access to education and providing personalized
learning experiences to every learner according to their needs.
In this course we'll delve into how our startup harnesses the power of Generative AI to unlock
new possibilities in education.
We'll also examine how they address the inevitable challenges tied to the social impact of this
technology and its technology limitations.
But let's start by defining some basic concepts we'll be using throughout the course.
Despite the recent types surrounding Generative AI, this technology has been decades in the
making with its origins tracing back to the 1950s, 1960s.
The earliest AI prototypes consisted of typewritten chatbots relying on knowledge bases maintained
by experts.
These chatbots generated responses based on keywords found in user input, but it soon
became clear that this approach had scalability limitations.
A significant turning point arrived in the 1990s, when a statistical approach was applied
to text analysis.
This gave birth to machine learning algorithms which could learn patterns from data without
explicit programming.
These algorithms allowed machines to simulate human language understanding, paving the way
for the AI we know today.
In more recent times, advancements in hardware technology allowed for the development of
advanced machine learning algorithms, particularly neural networks.
These innovations significantly improved natural language processing, enabling machines
to understand the context of words in sentences.
This breakthrough technology powered the birth of virtual assistants in the early 21st century.
And these virtual assistants excelled at interpreting human language, identifying needs, and taking
actions to fulfill them, such as answering queries with predefined scripts or connecting
to third-part services.
And so we arrived at Generative AI, a subset of deep learning.
After decades of AI research, a new model architecture known as the transformer emerged.
Transformers could handle longer text sequences as input and were based on the attention mechanism,
enabling them to focus on the most relevant information regardless of its order in a text.
Today, most generative AI models, often referred to as large-language models, are built upon
the transformer architecture.
These models, trained on vast amounts of data from sources like books, articles, and websites,
possess a unique adaptability.
They can tackle a wide range of tasks and generate grammatical correct text with a hint
of creativity.
But let's dive deeper into the mechanism of large-language models and shed light on
the inner workings of models like OpenAI, GPT.
One of the key concepts to grasp is tokenization.
Large-language models receive text as input and produce text as output.
However, these models work much more efficiently with numbers than with raw text sequences.
That's where the dokinizer comes into play.
A token is essentially a chunk of text which can vary in length and typically consist of
a sequence of characters.
The dokinizer's primary job is to break down the input text into an array of these tokens.
Once we have these tokens, they are further mapped to token indices.
And these token indices are essentially integer encodings of the original text chunks, making
it easier for the model to process and understand.
Now, let's move to predicting output tokens.
Given an input sequence of N tokens, with N barring from one model to another, the model
is designed to predict the single tokens as output.
But here's where it gets interesting.
The predicted token is then incorporated into the input of the next iteration, creating
an expanding window pattern.
And this pattern allows the model to provide more coherent and contextually relevant responses,
often extending to one or multiple sentences.
Finally, let's delve into the selection process.
The model chooses the output token base on its probability of occurring after the current
text sequence.
This probability distribution is calculating using the model's training data.
However, here's the twist.
The model does always choose the token with the highest probability from the distribution.
To simulate the process of creative thinking, a degree of randomness is introduced into
the selection process.
And this means that the model doesn't produce the exact same output for the same input every
time.
And that's the element that allows generative AI to generate text that feels creative and
engaging.
We say that the main capability of a large language model is generating a text from scratch,
starting from a textual input written in natural language.
But what kind of textual input and output?
First of all, let me say that the input of a large language model is known as prompt,
while the output is known as completion, term that refers to the model mechanism of generating
the next token to complete the current input.
Let's do some examples of prompts and completions by using the OpenAI chatGBT playground.
A prompt may include an instruction specifying the type of output we expect from the model,
such as a request to write an assignment for high school students including four open-ended
questions about Louis XIV and his court.
A prompt might also include a question asked in the form of a conversation with an agent,
like who is Louis XIV and why he is an important historical character.
Another example of prompt is a chunk of text to complete, which implicitly is an ask for
writing assistance.
The examples I just did are quite simple and won't be an exhaustive demonstration of large
language models capabilities.
They just want to show the potential of using generative AI, in particular but not limited
to the educational context.
That's all for this lesson.
In the following lesson, we're going to explore different types of generative AI models and
we're going to cover how to test, iterate to improve performance and compare different
models to find the most suitable for a specific use case.