hi everyone and welcome to the first
lesson of the generative AI for
beginners course this course is based on
an open source curriculum with the same
name available on gab I'm Carlota cucho
AI Cloud Advocate at Microsoft and in
this video I'm going to introduce you to
generative Ai and large language
models large language models represent
the Pinnacle of AI technology pushing
the boundaries of what was once thought
impossible they've concered numerous
challenges that older language models
struggled with achieving human level
performance in various task they have
several capabilities and applications
but for this course we'll explore how
large language models are
revolutionizing education through a
fictional startup that we'll be
referring to as our startup our startup
works in the education domain with the
ambitious mission of improving
accessibility in learning on a global
scale ensuring Equitable access to
education and providing personalized
learning experiences to every learner
according to their needs in this course
we'll dive into how our startup
harnesses the power of generative AI to
unlock new possibilities in education
we'll also examine how to address the
inevitable challenges tied to the social
impact of these technology and its
technology
limitations but let's start by defining
some basic concept with will be using
throughout the
course despite the recent hype
surrounding gen AI this technology has
been decades in the making with its
Origins tressing back to the 1950s
1960s the earliest AI prototypes
consisted of typewritten chatbots
relying on knowledge bases maintained by
experts these chatbots generated
responses based on keywords found in
user input but it soon became clear that
this approach had scalability Li
itations a significant Turning Point
arrived in the 1990s when a statistical
approach was applied to text analysis
this gave birth to Mach learning
algorithms which could learn pattern
from data without explicit programming
these algorithms allowed machines to
simulate human language understanding
Paving the way for the AI we know today
in more recent times advancements in
Hardware technology allowed for the
development of advanced masch learning
algorith particularly neural networks
these Innovation significantly improved
natural language processing enabling
machines to understand the context of
words in
sentences this breakthrough technology
powered the birth of viritual assistance
in the early 21st century and this
virtual assistance excelled at
interpreting human language identifying
needs and taking actions to fulfill them
such as answering queries with
predefined scripts or connecting to
third part services and so we arrived at
generative AI a subset of deep learning
after Decades of AI research a new model
architecture known as the Transformer
emerged Transformers could handle longer
tax sequences as input and were based on
the attention mechanism enabling them to
focus on the most relevant information
regardless of its order in the text
today most generative AI models often
referred to as large language models are
built upon the Transformer AR Ure these
models train on vast amounts of data
from sources like books articles and
websites possess a unique adaptability
they can tackle a wide range of task and
generate grammatical correct text with a
hint of
creativity but let's dive deeper into
the mechanism of large language models
and shed light on the inner workings of
models like open
GPT one of the key Concepts to grasp is
tokenization
large language models receive text as
input and produce text as output however
these models work much more efficiently
with numbers than withdraw text
sequences that's where the tokenizer
comes into play a token is essentially a
chunk of text which can vary in length
and typically consist of a sequence of
characters the tokenizer primary job is
to break down the input tax into an
array of these
tokens once we have these tokens they
are further ma to token indices and
these token indices are essentially
integer and codings of the original text
Chance making it easier for the model to
process and
understand now let's move to predicting
output tokens given an input sequence of
n tokens with n baring from one model to
another the model is designed to predict
a single tokens as output but here
here's where it gets interesting the
predicted token is then incorporated
into the input of the next iteration
creating an expanding window pattern and
this pattern allows the model to provide
more coherent and contextually relevant
responses often extending to one or
multiple
sentences finally let's dive into the
selection process the model chooses the
output token based on its probability of
occurring after the current text
sequence this probability distribution
is calculating using the model's
training
data however here's the twist the model
does always choose the token with the
highest probability from the
distribution to simulate the process of
creative thinking a degree of Randomness
is introduced into the selection process
and this means that the model doesn't
produce the exact same output for the
same input every time and that's the
element that allows gener TBI to
generate text that feels creative and
engaging we say that the main capability
of a large language model is generating
a text from scratch starting from a
textual input written in natural
language but but what kind of textual
input and output first of all let me say
that the input of a large language model
is known as prompt while the output is
known as completion term that refers to
the model mechanism of generating the
next token to complete the current input
let's do some examples of prompts and
completions by using the openai CH gbt
playground a prompt may include an
instruction specifying the type of
output we expect from the model such as
a request to write an assignment for
high school students including four
open-ended questions about Louis 14th
and this
court a prompt might also include a
question asked in the form of a
conversation with an agent like who is
Louis 14th and why he is an important
historical
character another example of prompt is a
chunk of text to complete which
implicitly is an ask for writing
assistance the examples I justed are
quite simple and won't be an exhaustive
demonstration of large language models
capabilities they just want to show the
potential of using generative AI in
particular but not limited to the
educational
context that's all for this lesson in
the following lesson we are going to
explore different types of generative AI
models and we're going to cover how to
test iterate to improve performance and
compare different models to find the
most suitable for a specific use case